A Guide to the Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Joseph C.G. Kennedy, Census Office, writes about various properties (1847 Jun 17); recommends that Mr. Hall be sent to Richmond to retake the census for that city (1851 Apr 2); mentions Alexander H. H. Stuart 's election to the National Institute (1851 Apr 8); beginning in May of 1851, he writes six letters during his trip to Europe to study the European use of statistics and their use in legislation, the census, and agricultural production; visits the Statistical Society of London and discusses the ratio of representation, fractions, and population (1851 Jun 3); visits the President of the Board of Trade to get information on the true basis of statistical knowledge (1851 Jun 10); urged to stay and address the British Association for the Promotion of Science of which Prince Albert was President, his visits to some of the foremost statistical men connected to British government offices and other nations such as Prussia, France, and Belgium (1851 Jun 23); his description of Berlin and Wittenberg, recommendation that a Bureau of Agriculture & Statistics be created along the lines of those in France and Belgium, prediction that America will march to a degree of honor and prosperity that will far exceed any of the old world (1851 Aug 7); on recommendation of Baron Humboldt he plans to visit Vienna (1851 Aug 17); at home, the mania for rail and plank roads, political news of Pennsylvania, and his expectation that the Scott Whigs will carry the Presidency (1852 Oct 16); discusses the political race between Scott and Harrison in the region of Pittsburgh ([?] Oct 12)
Kent Lumber Company concerning the payment of drafts incurred by federal agencies (1852 Oct 27)
Andrew W. Kercheval with a genealogical inquiry about James Wood, a Revolutionary General and Virginia Governor (1867 Feb 14)
William Kerr seeking whiskey patronage (1851 Nov 14)
Samuel D. King about California affairs, blames the Whig government for neglecting the state and predicts bad consequences for the upcoming election (1851 Jul 14)
Jefferson Kinney all three letters deal with business matters such as the sale of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's lots in Staunton for a railroad passenger depot and possible benefits to the town from the railroad (1852)
Nicholas Kinney refers to the speech of [Mr. Nathaniel Pitcher Tallmadge ?] concerning the Bankruptcy Bill, the Locofocos, his disappointment with his friend [ Thomas Walker?] Gilmer, the conversion of David W. Patteson, who is a possible candidate for Congress, to Methodism (1841 Sep 3); sends a copy of letter from the Rev. B.M. Smith concerning a rumor that Alexander H. H. Stuart contradicted his statement about Dr. Ticknor's qualifications as assistant physician at the Asylum (1851 Feb 18 & 26); the strong position of the Whig party at present (1851 Feb 26)
R.H. Kinney asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to pursue the military claim of the heirs of Dr. Roberts (1841 Jun 25)
William Kinney reports on several court cases and discusses political appointments, especially Mr. Hagarty for the Liverpool consulate, and Alexander H. H. Stuart 's vote to rescind the 21 rule (1841 Jun 13); complains about the behavior of the Whig Congress so far, discusses Alexander H. H. Stuart 's outline of his plan of operations for this session and not fixing the ratio of representation under the new census for the next Congress, his fear that the Locofocos will gain influence in the Virginia State Legislature, the resignation of "Extra Billy" [Governor William Smith ] from his seat in the Senate and his hopes that the House of Representatives would give the seat to Extra "for really I consider him a great nuisance in the Senate," believes that Webster's objections to the appointment of Hagarty to the consulate of Liverpool not valid as he [wrongly !] thinks Nicholas Trist was born in Louisiana and is not a Virginian, and discusses his [Kentz?] suit at length (1841 Jun 23); argues that the success of the suit of Porterfield vs Clark hinges on proving that the country in question belonged to the Cherokees in 1779, found out that Silas E. Burrows is the favorite of Webster for the Liverpool consulate, while the leading merchants of New York favor Hagarty, and says Tucker will accept the professorship of law on condition that they will let him reside out of the precincts of the University [of Virginia] (1841 Jul 22); reports that they have just finished the battle for Speaker of the Virginia Legislature with the election of [Valentine Wood] Southall considered a Whig victory, "we had a long, I cannot say very able or palatable message from the accidental Gov. of Virginia -coming into office as he did, he ought to have been modest" (1841 Dec 6); notes that the introduction of a batch of Federal resolutions into the House have alarmed the Locofocos, especially the one urging the repeal of the Distribution Act, which is popular in the Western part of the state, and discusses the prospects of several men for the Governorship of Virginia (1841 Dec 24); reports on election results in Augusta County, urges Alexander H. H. Stuart to write some articles on the Tariff to attract the support of the young farmers and mechanics which are being courted by the Democrats as new voters under the new state constitution (1851 Oct 24); discusses the legal case of Woods vs Brooks and expresses his confidence in the election of General Scott (1852 Jul 13); discusses the election of cashier at the Bank and the appointment of a marshall for the western district of Virginia (1852 Nov 12 & 30); and discusses the affairs of the Staunton Bank, of which he is President, and the Central Railroad (1852 Dec 23)
O.B. Knode asks Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence be used to have Colonel Tiernan appointed to a judgeship in Utah (1852 Jan 22)
F.A. Kownslar writes concerning a debt (1833 Jun 24)
Daniel Kraber concerning the will of George Lightner with a copy of the will attached (1831 Nov 15)
J.D. Kurtz concerning cadet appointments (1853 Jan 17)
John H.B. Latrobe appreciates Alexander H. H. Stuart 's speech and the exposition of the operation of the partnership principle by Alexander H. H. Stuart (1838 Sep 1)
Joseph S. Leake inquires about the price of one of Mr. Alexander H. H. Stuart 's houses (1831 Nov 3)
Adam Lee about taking up a land agency in the Transalleghany country (1831 Mar 11)
John Letcher (1813-1884) hopes Alexander H. H. Stuart has received the seeds sent by his friend Whiting (1856 May 2)
[Will H. Lewis ?], State Department, sends invitation to dine (n.d.)
John Tayloe Lomax asks which states are a good market for legal books, expresses his opinion of the need for a protective tariff, his hope that Henry Clay will run as the Whig candidate for President, and the appearance that John C. Calhoun was the most prominent of the Locofocos (1842 Jul 8)
L. Luckett describes his family's trip to Memphis, [Tennessee] (1859 Aug 1); mentions seeing the manufacture of weapons in Richmond and his trip to New Orleans during the Civil War, the condition of the cotton crop, benefits of the war in uniting the South, the vast difference between the Southerners and the Yankees, the ironclad [Thunderbolt ?] expected to leave New Orleans this week to go against Fort St. Phillip and Jackson (1861 Sep 2); refers to negotiations with England by the South and refers to slavery "our peculiar institution that they hoped was our weakness, is a tower of strength." (1861 Dec 23)
James Lyons appreciates Alexander H. H. Stuart 's speech upon the subject of a national Bank and recommends the establishment of an Exchange Bank with branches in all of the states and regrets the division that the Bank issue has brought between the executive and legislative branches (1841 Aug 20)
Joseph S. Machie both letters discuss getting the deposition of James M.H. Beale for a trial (1851-1852)
James MacDonald wants his younger brother appointed a surgeon either in the Navy or Army (1851 Oct 8)
Redick McKee reports on the progress of the Commission sent to California to visit the hundreds of small Indian tribes and families, his plans to soon visit the tribes along the Mercede River, Mariposa County, the condition of the Whig Party in California, the upcoming Senatorial contest, and his desire for the San Francisco Custom House position if it comes open (1851 Jan 28); reports signing the first treaty between the United States and the California Indians at Camp Fremont on March 19th with six tribes and the possibility of a treaty with two more tribes near Fresno River, the poor quality of the soil, and his poor opinion of Dr. Wozencraft, California Indian agent (1851 Mar 21); recommends pacifying the Indians with a liberal supply of beef and flour, his disagreement with Wozencraft who entered into a contract with Fremont, a political opponent, to supply beef to the Indians before the treaties were ratified by Congress and signed by the President, mentions other scandals and improprieties in the Indian agency of California, and feels that reorganization of the whole governmental system in California is necessary (1851 Jun 30); desires the newly created position of "Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Pacific Coast" and criticizes the appointment of Lt. Beall as Indian Commissioner for California because he is known as a Democrat (1852 Mar 17 & May 5)
Thomas M.S. McKennan letter of introduction for William Mills (1851 Oct 29)
Lewis McKenzie asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to speak before the Bell & Everett Club as a friend of the Union (1860 Aug 31)
William McLaughlin asks if Staunton will support the invitation by the Franklin Club, Washington College, and the Virginia Military Institute, to Edward Everett to speak in Lexington in order to raise money to purchase Mount Vernon (1857 Nov 23)
Theodorick B. McRobert thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for the clerkship in the Department of the Interior (1850 Oct 3); includes a letter from Archibald B. Walker concerning a possible pension based on the Revolutionary War service of Alexander Walker (1850 Nov 26 & 1851 Jan 8); includes a letter from the Rev. Luther Emerson, of Cob Bottom, Highland County, who promises to write a series of essays on the Scriptural view of slavery if McRobert will help him get some Northern Whig newspapers to print them (1851 Dec 18 & 26)
F. Madera requests a promotion in the Pension Office (1851 Dec 30)
Allan B. Magruder writes to secure a cadetship for his son, John T. Magruder, at West Point, and asks for a letter of introduction to the Secretary of the Navy on behalf of his brother, Captain Magruder (1851-1853); he also expresses his disappointment that Millard Fillmore did not receive the nomination at the Baltimore Convention (1852 Jun 24)
James Maguire accuses Mr. Bartlett, the Mexican Boundary Survey Commissioner, of embezzling (1851 Mar 29)
Francis Mallory (1807-1860) congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to the Cabinet (1851 Jun 13); discusses the case of Mr. Kyle of Norfolk and criticizes Mr. Eubank and his staff over his handling of Kyle's case (1852); and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that the Whigs of Norfolk want the postmaster position to go to John P. Leigh when Mr. Cohen dies (1852 Sep 29)
N. Marmion to Messrs. Baldwin & Stuart, Attorneys-at-Law, concerning the debt of George Nicholson (1834 Mar 6 & Aug 21)
Timothy Marmion writes concerning business matters (n.y. Dec 21)
J.K. Marshall writes concerning a debt owed by Messrs. Harman & Garber (1852 Jan 30)
Thomas A. Marshall inquires if Alexander H. H. Stuart can help him determine if James M. Moffit is deceased, Moffit was a plaintiff in the legal case of Miller heirs vs Boatman (1833)
Thomas Martin notifies Alexander H. H. Stuart that his father, Pleasant Martin, has moved to Tennessee (1830 Jul 27)
William Martin discusses the upcoming Virginia election for governor and the need for Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont to convince the Legislature to fix the question of the payment of the interest on the public debt (1867 Feb 10)
Maryland Institute Officers & Managers ask Alexander H. H. Stuart to deliver their "Annual Address" at the opening of the Annual Exhibition of Manufacturers & Machinery (1851 Oct 6)
James Murray Mason (1798-1871) regrets that he does not have any of the published documents concerning the Wheeling Bridge case, excepting the Congressional Globe at home (1853 Oct 22)
[John Young] Mason (1799-1859) recommending John Dabney for some Federal government position (1851 Dec 30)
Colonel James W. Massie writes concerning a debt owed to Hugh McClure (1871 Apr 17)
Thomas E. Massie, Santa Fe, New Mexico, introduces D.V. Whiting, as knowledgeable of modern languages (1852 May 5)
Joel E. Matthews writes concerning the legal case of Matthews vs Minzes (1851-1852)
Tyre Maupin informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that the Rough and Ready Club of Rockingham County plan to present him with a silver pitcher for his services to the Whig Party (1848 Sep 3); asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart knows whether James Madison ever offered a Cabinet position to General Scott and informs him that he plans to vote for Scott now that he has the Whig nomination (1852 Jul 17)
R. Mayo asks for a favorable review of his book now before the Pension Committee of the Senate (1852)
Thompson G. Martin writes concerning his efforts to sell some Alexander H. H. Stuart land for them in Scott County, Virginia, and Tennessee (1831, 1834)
Members of the Virginia Legislature names Whig candidates favored by themselves for several positions (n.d.)
Memoranda of A.H.H. Stuart while Secretary of the Interior, chiefly concerning appointments and removals for positions in the government under his jurisdiction (ca. 1851-1853)
C.F. Mercer, President of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company, writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart as their representative (1832 May 28)
Hugh Mercer asks Daniel Webster to transfer his son, George Weedon Mercer, from the Second Auditor's Office, to the State Department (1851 Feb 22 & Jul 4)
[S.]C.M. Merillat asks Alexander H. H. Stuart if he knows if Congress plans on raising the duties on foreign iron in the near future as he has interests in an iron rolling mill and they need to decide what to do with it now that it has suspended operations (1852 Jun 1)
C.H. Merritt sends Alexander H. H. Stuart a ring made out of native gold of New Mexico (1851 Sep 30) and introduces Judge Houghton of New Mexico (1851 Oct 20)
Thomas J. Michie (1795-1873) writes concerning various legal cases (1845 Aug 1; 1850 Dec 19; 1852 Jan 18 & 29 and Oct 15); congratulates him on his appointment to the Cabinet and expresses his hopes that the Administration will benefit from any good will generated by the Compromise of 1850, his regret at being without Alexander H. H. Stuart 's companionship during his stay in Washington, and offers to help with any of his legal cases when he is not on the other side (1850 Sep 15); thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for his gift, comments on the recent election, "for I could not but believe that a majority of the new made vote would be Democratic, & I knew the power of the party which, to make men forget every excellence, & carry out the behests of the party...nor are the Whigs less the slaves of such machinery than the Democrats," discusses the plight of Hungarian patriot and statesman, Lajos Kossuth (1802-1894), and mentions "the young Napoleon" [ Napoleon III ] (1851 Dec 29); sends a printed copy of his points of law, made in the appeal case of Points, assignee of Hottle vs Crawford, and discusses the case (1852 Jan 14)
William C. Micou asks for his assistance in a case now before the Supreme Court (1852 Oct 20)
Daniel F. Miller to Thomas Corwin -asks for Isaac Leffler (1788-1866), a former Whig member of Congress from Virginia, to be appointed to one of the land districts in Iowa; President Millard Fillmore appointed him receiver of public moneys for the Chariton land district of Iowa on August 30th (1852 Aug 17)
Jacob Welsh Miller (1800-1862) introduces George P. [?], of New Jersey, a member of the U.S. & Mexican Boundary Commission (1852 May 5)
James Miller asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to intervene with John P. Kennedy on his brother's behalf for an appointment in the Navy Department (1852 Dec 1)
Zophar Mills, Chairman of the Seventh Ward Democratic Whig Association of the City of New York, encloses a copy of the Preamble and Constitution of the Association (1851 Jul 8)
Joseph L. Mitchell acknowledges the receipt of the agricultural book (1852 Feb 7)
John Moebus requests Alexander H. H. Stuart to furnish him with the money to reach New York (1852 Jun 22)
John Moffett writes concerning his unhappiness over the nomination of General Winfield Scott and his fears of a military candidate and Roman Catholics in the election (1852 Jun 27)
Thomas S. Moffett, cousin of Alexander H. H. Stuart, requests he send one hundred dollars to Richmond (1834 Jan 27)
Henry W. Moncure asks for a letter of introduction to Abbott Lawrence, the United States Minister to Great Britain, to facilitate his tour of Europe (1852 Jun 9)
Charles P. Montague volunteers to carry dispatches abroad for the Federal government (1852 Jun 8)
D.E. Moore expresses dismay at the election of John Tyler as President (1841 Aug 26)
John K. Moore asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart remember his son, John B. Moore, who was unable to continue his plan of working in the mines due to dysentery caught while waiting in Panama for a ship, if any appointments open up in California (1850 Nov 27); and expresses his disgust at the nomination of General Scott (1852 Jul 6)
L.T. Moore writes concerning the Beeler family estate (1851 Oct 10,18, 21)
Samuel McDowell Moore writes letters concerning political events in Virginia and the Virginia Legislature, including: the "Senatorial Lottery," his own possible candidacy for office in the Virginia Senate to oppose the "unworthy" David W. Patteson, a bill for a Railroad from Staunton to Harpers Ferry to Baltimore, the reorganization of the courts, and his opposition to amalgamating the Common Law and Chancery Court (1830 Jan 24); his busy schedule with the Committee on Elections which sent Barbour and Davis back to try again, returning the elections to the people for a revote, with no information about Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Senator (1830 Dec 25); passage of the Railway Bill from Staunton to the Potomac, and tells about the nephew of Chief Justice John Marshall shooting and killing William Gott after he refused to duel with him (1831 Feb 23-24); news that Jefferson [Kinney?] plans to run as a candidate for the Senate against Patteson and his own indecision about whether to run as well (1831 Mar 2); thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for his opinions about Moore running for the Virginia Senate in order to unseat David W. Patteson, speaks about his opposition to the odious amendment to Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Railroad Bill introduced into the House of Delegates which prohibited the government from subscribing to any part of the stock, the 29th section of the bill was stricken out, discusses all of his work to secure the passage of the bill as Alexander H. H. Stuart submitted it, and mentions the Judiciary Bill (1831 Mar 17); discusses the bill affecting court clerk fees, his decision not to run for the Virginia Senate seat, and the Railroad Bill (1831 Apr 10); furnishes his opinion of the elections at Rockbridge and Augusta, Mr. Dorman's efforts for David W. Patteson and against his own candidate (1831 Jun 30, Jul 4 & 5); discusses the bill for internal improvements, the work of the Special Committee regarding the subject of removing free Negroes and Mulattoes, the emancipation of slaves, the majority of the Committee refused to pay for the Negroes killed in Southampton, and other propositions concerning slaves and their removal from western Virginia (1832 Jan 5); following Moore's election to the House of Representatives, he believes the followers of Martin Van Buren have the political advantage, the President seems anxious to get Daniel Webster into the Democratic Party in order to carry the Senate in their favor, Nullifiers also want Webster to switch parties to alienate Southerners, destroy the Union, and establish a Southern Confederacy, the inadvisability of Henry Clay running for President, and mention of Richard M. Johnson of Kentucky as a probable candidate for Vice-President with Van Buren (1833 Dec 24); discusses the election of [Littleton Waller] Tazewell (1774-1860) as evidence that the "Old Dominion" is dead set against Martin Van Buren for President and other political matters, and includes an amusing story of his social life (1834 Jan 11); his concern over the Banking Bill and false accusations against Moore printed by the editor of The Fincastle Patriot 1834 Apr 7); encouraged by the results of the Virginia elections and other political gossip (1834 May 20); discusses the resolutions regarding the Sub-Treasury scheme, Calhoun's speech supporting the scheme, and Clay's speech against it and Calhoun, and mention of the Locofoco Party (1838 Feb 22); some of the Whigs uneasy over Alexander H. H. Stuart 's vote on the 21st Rule which vote Moore approved, "I consider the true ground on which to meet the abolitionists is that they are prohibited by the Constitution from interfering with our domestic concerns, and we should meet them on the ramparts of the Constitution. And not in endeavoring to defend a rule of order of at least doubtful justice and propriety," and furnishes his version of the history of the "abolition humbug" beginning with General Jackson kicking Calhoun out of the "Kitchen Cabinet" and continuing with Calhoun's attempt to fan the flames of sectional division for his own political purposes; and his belief that the Whigs should pass Mr. Ewing's Bank Bill with as little alteration as possible, and mentions Extra Billy Smith 's letter expressing his opinion that Tyler will veto any bill chartering a U.S. Bank (1841 June 22); the defeat of the Bank Bill in Congress, Tyler's attack on the Whig Party as the enemy of States' Rights, the controversy over the nature of the proposed National Bank and his own solution to the problem, and his contention that the Bankruptcy Bill should not be passed at present (1841 Aug 22); complains about [John Minor] Botts giving Whigs a bad name, discusses flaws in the Bank Bill, notes that Whigs are dissatisfied with [William Cabell ?] Rives course in countering the Whig Party, and complains about [Henry Alexander ?] Wise (1841 Aug 27); and discusses the Firebaugh Will legal case (1850 Oct 18; 1852 Jan 5 & Mar 16)
John Moorman recommends the Rev. Samuel R. Houston as Superintendent of the Deaf and Dumb Asylum at Staunton, Virginia (1852 Mar 4)
[W.?] Morris seeks a position in the State Department (1852 Dec 1)
C.L. Mosby writes concerning claims against the Thomas Wells estate (1831 May 18); and asks if he knows of a purser position in the Navy for his brother, William W. Mosby (1851 Dec 15)
[Alexander] Moseley expresses his concern with President Tyler and Edward Everett 's reply to the abolitionists (1841 Jul-Aug); discusses the idea of acquiring Cuba from Spain and the widespread aversion to Spanish rule in Cuba and his hopes that [John Minor ?] Botts would not be elected (1851 Jun 13 & Oct 20); believes that Millard Fillmore will be nominated at the Baltimore Convention (1852 Mar 20); the need for a full Whig vote in Virginia to defeat Franklin Pierce (1852 Oct 5 & 7)
J.W. Myers questions Stuart about the meaning of President Millard Fillmore 's latest message in regard to military intervention on behalf of the Hungarian Lajos Kossuth or in any European conflict (1851 Dec 11)
Thomas Nairu writes concerning federal appointments in Iowa (1850 Oct 23)